All right, בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*. We begin a new מסכתא masechta.
*Masechta* today. Today's דף Daf *Daf* is כתובות Ketuvot *Kesuvos*, דף daf
א *Daf Aleph* and ב *Beis*, and I'll say just one or
two brief words about כתובות Ketuvot *Kesuvos*. You know, we just finished
מסכת Masechet יבמות *Masechet Yevamos* and there's like a saying in the
ישיבה yeshiva *Yeshiva* world that there are three מסכתות Masechtot *Masechtot* that
will sort of that'll like wipe you out, and they are and
the acronym is עני *Ani*, so it's it makes you poor.
They're called עירובין *Eruvin*, נדה niddah, *Niddah*, and יבמות *Yevamos*. So so
far we've done two, if you've been with us since the beginning,
עירובין *Eruvin* and יבמות *Yevamos*. So we've only got נדה niddah, *Niddah*
which we'll leave till the very end. So anyway, so that's in
terms of יבמות *Yevamos* and how sort of challenging it was particularly
the beginning. I mean, the middle and the end was I thought,
you know, very relevant and engaging and so on, but the beginning
in particular and all that some elements of it were always very,
very challenging. כתובות Ketuvot, *Kesuvos*, on the other hand, is known in
the ישיבה *Yeshiva* world as the ש״ס קטן *Shas Katan*, the little
mini ש״ס *Shas*, because it has so many diverse ש״ס *Shas* concepts
that come up in the context of its other discussions. The primary
topic of כתובות Ketuvot. *Kesuvos*, one could say is a כתובה Ketubah.
*Kesuvah*, but not really. It's you know the primary topic of it
is the state of נשואין Nisuin. *Nisuin* as opposed to קידושין Kiddushin,
*Kiddushin*. Right, so קידושין Kiddushin *Kiddushin* is the actual giving of the
ring, I mean, that's what we do nowadays, which makes them legally
married, which means that the woman afterwards if the woman were to
commit adultery, as if she were to sleep with another man, it
would be an act of adultery. So they are completely legally married,
but they haven't started living together. That's חופה Chuppah. *Chuppah*, that's נשואין
Nisuin. *Nisuin*. That would often happen, people say a year later, but
actually we're going to sort of get to it today's דף *Daf*,
it could sometimes be many years later. It could be that the
קידושין Kiddushin *Kiddushin* was arranged with the father, קטנה *Ketana*, not just
arranged, but was effected with the father and many years before they're
actually ready, you know, but that makes it binding, and then they
actually start living together many years later and that's the moment of
חופה Chuppah *Chuppah*. So what we do standing under the חופה Chuppah
*Chuppah* is like symbolic of actual practical living together, setting up home
and so on. Partly, of course, that's being the idea of of
having sex, but it's also just of setting up house together. So
the חופה chuppah *Chuppah*, you know, if you want to think about
the difference between the חופה chuppah, *Chuppah* and the ייחוד *Yichud* room,
one is sort of that coming into living in a home together
and the other is starting to have a sexual life, and that
is the period of נשואין Nisuin, *Nisuin*. Now a major part of
that is the reciprocal obligations that kick in once it is not
just a legally binding marriage, but once actually it is a marriage
in fact, not just in law. You know, once they actually start
living together as a married couple and that's when you have a
lot of the reciprocal obligations. The husband's obligation to provide food and
lodging and מצות עונה *Mitzvat Onah*, regular sex at particular intervals and
so on. And the wife's obligations to the husband, particularly the ones
that the rabbis created, like that her earnings would go to her
husband. Other types of obligations, you know, we'll get to it when
we discuss it that they're not parallel but they're reciprocal and reflect
certain realities of society, certain economic realities, social realities, some of those
things can change when those realities change, we'll discuss all that. But
those are the reciprocal types of financial obligations and other obligations like
the מצוה *Mitzvah* of עונה *Onah* is not financial. Okay, so that's
part of what happens so that's a major new halakhic issues that
kick in, obligations, realities that kick in at the time of נשואין
Nisuin *Nisuin*. Those are actually called תנאי כתובה Ketubah *Tnai Kesuvah*. תנאי
*Tnai* sometimes can mean a condition. This will only take place on
the following condition, but here it means like the stipulations of the
כתובה Ketubah, *Kesuvah*, the ongoing obligations that are in
the
כתובה Ketubah, *Kesuvah*. And then there's the other part to כתובה Ketubah
*Kesuvah*, which is the 200 or 100 זוז zuz *zuz* and other
types of things, which would happen if they get divorced or if
the husband died, the type of alimony payment that the wife would
collect in the case of divorce, or if the husband were to
die, according to תורה *Torah* law and even rabbinic law, the wife
doesn't inherit her husband, but instead what she would do is she
would take this money, this lump sum out of the estate. So
that would be considered the עיקר כתובה ketubah *Ikar Kesuvah*, the 200
or the 100 זוז zuz *zuz*. And then the final, that's two
parts: so one part of the כתובה Ketubah *Kesuvah* is the ongoing
reciprocal obligations, one part is this lump sum, 200 or 100 זוז
zuz, *zuz* which would be paid out at death or if he
died first, or at divorce. And then the third part is it
would list the property that she brought into the marriage for her
dowry and that then she would be able to take out of
the marriage again at the time of death or divorce. Okay, so
those are like the three major parts of the כתובה ketubah, *Kesuvah*,
and it's called כתובות Ketubot *Kesuvos* because this מסכת Masechet. *Masechet* deals
with all of those, not just with the document of the כתובה
ketubah *Kesuvah*, but with all of those pieces of it. And a
lot of those pieces by the way, are true and are binding
whether or not any document was written. The reciprocal reciprocal obligations exist
even if they never wrote a כתובה. ketubah, His lump-sum obligation exists
even if they never wrote a כתובה. Okay, but these things, fine,
but these things are written in the document but they are like
so in a way כתובות really is the types of halakhic obligations
that exist as a result of them actually beginning to live together
as a married couple, as a result of נשואין. Okay, so that
is a what the sort of major theme of כתובות is, it
is the state of נשואין. We will get later to קידושין, Kiddushin,
which is the actual binding act of marriage that makes them legally
married, but does not yet start the living together with the whole
ongoing obligations. The reason קידושין Kiddushin. comes later is as you know
the מסכתות masechtot are ordered by size, defined by number of chapters.
So therefore קידושין Kiddushin, comes later, and before we even get to
קידושין, Kiddushin we have גיטין Gittin coming after כתובות, which is bigger
than the מסכת Masechet קידושין. Kiddushin, So it's a little strange order,
but that's the basic topic of כתובות. Those are the primary themes,
but as I said, if it were just for that it wouldn't
be called the ש"ס קטן, Shas Katan, you know, it would be
like a lot of interesting local laws like גיטין, Gittin, but there
are a lot of interesting things that do come up along the
way. I should just mention that one big area is the whole
discussions of קים ליה בדרבה מיניה, Kam lei b'derabba minei, which is
because there's issues about paying the קנס Knas if a man rapes
a woman, an unmarried woman, or seduces her, he pays a fine.
That fine is linked to the payment that the money that she
would have gotten, the כתובה money that a groom would have obligated
himself to, would have been responsible for at marriage, and now because
she's like gonna be seen as damaged property, she won't have that,
so he has to pay that. So that's why we have this
whole discussion of that category, and that's a basic source, one of
the main sources of the idea of כתובה, of this lump-sum payment,
is learned from those פרשיות Parshiyot of rape and seduction. So that's
why those make up some, you know, a section of this מסכת.
Masechet, And then that deals with all these interesting questions about what
are times when he wouldn't pay it because he did a worse
sin through this act of sex, and that's קים ליה בדרבה מיניה
Kam lei b'derabba minei when some type of a larger sin, a
larger, you know, a more serious act outweighs a financial payment and
so on. So that's just one example of ways in which larger
ש"ס Shas concepts intersect with this issue. I'll just give one other
example, which is witnesses that are forced to sign a document or
that claim that a document that they signed it when they were
minors, or that they were, you know, when can they retract their
testimony of a signed document? Because we're dealing with this signed document,
the כתובה, so those are issues that come up, you know, in
מסכת כתובות, Masechet Ketuvot, and as you can imagine, are much larger
ש"ס Shas concepts. Okay, so we both have really fascinating concrete specific
issues in terms of the realities of marriage, not the act of
not wedding,
not the legally binding קידושין, Kiddushin but the reality of marriage and
the legal aspects of it, and then these larger ש"ס Shas concepts
as well. It's a מסכת that is learned a lot in ישיבות
Yeshivot for that reason,
and there's the whole wealth of ראשונים Rishonim that are on this
מסכת, although you won't see them all on the דף that we
are doing. Okay, so we are now going to start. Michael already
has a question, we haven't read the first word. Go ahead.
You mentioned the three things, so in our modern כתובה none of
it lists like the property she's bringing in, right? I mean is
that done at all?
It's a pro forma list of property she's bringing in. We'll get
to discuss it when we get to it. Okay, but when it
says בין בכסף בין בזהב בין בתכשיטין, Bein b'chesef bein b'zahav bein
b'tachshitin, it's sort of saying all the property you brought in, and
we're not going to list it now, is worth X amount, but
we don't actually specifically concretely list it.
Okay, so you said the קידושין Kiddushin, is the legal marriage?
Yes, completely considered a married woman and like with the consequences about
again if she were to sleep with another man it would be
adultery, but it's just that you don't have the actual like they're
not it's not a they're not living together so you don't have
the right types of reciprocal obligations that exist in a real, when
the marriage is really real. All right, and we're actually going to
touch on that right now at the beginning. So let's take a
look. בתולה נישאת ליום הרביעי. Betulah niset l'yom ha-revi'i.
A virgin would have her נשואין, not the קידושין, Kiddushin right? The
קידושין kiddushin, is whenever they wanted to have the קידושין, kiddushin that
was like I said very formal
and technical, but this נשואין would be the חופה. chuppah The חופה
chuppah, would be the real שמחה. Simcha. By the way, like for
example think about the שבע ברכות, Sheva Brachot,
here's an interesting thing to think about, right? The קידושין kiddushin could
just be the guy with the girl's father when she's a minor,
it's a contract, like it's just a legal act, we're going to
ensure that we're going to get married, but it doesn't become real
yet, right? That could have been ten years ago and that could
have been when the girl was a minor. The when it becomes
real is the חופה chuppah and that's when you involve and that's
when you have the major סעודה, Seudah, you have a major communal
event. שבע ברכות Sheva Brachot requires a מנין, Minyan, requires there to
be ten people. The שבע ברכות Sheva Brachot are the blessings of
the community to the חתן וכלה. Chatan v'Kallah. The ברכה Bracha of
אירוסין Eirusin is a much more private ברכה, Bracha, does not require
a מנין. Minyan. So then... The actual community participates not in the
act of קידושין, kiddushin. but in the act of חופה chuppah. and
in the act of נישואין, nisuin, that was the public communal event,
that was the event the שמחה, simcha, that was the event where
you had a big, where you had a big סעודה, seudah, right?
We obviously do both, okay? But I'm just saying it because who
knows when you got married? The קידושין kiddushin. took place whenever it
took place. We're going to talk about when they would actually have
the חופה, chuppah which was, you know, even on the wedding invitation
it says חופה chuppah, will be at this time, right? So that's
the חופה, chuppah. that's the נישואין. nisuin. קידושין kiddushin. was ten years
ago, here's when the חופה chuppah? will be at four. Yes?
Probably you do need עדים edim for קידושין. kiddushin You need עדים
edim for קידושין. kiddushin It's more clearly...
yeah, it's not correct, it's not totally private,
and actually it's much...
you definitely need עדים edim for קידושין. kiddushin It's not at all
clear that you need formal עדים edim for the חופה. chuppah We
do, we have like עדי יחוד edei yichud and so on, but
because the חופה chuppah might just be the reality of them living
together, the actualization of the קידושין kiddushin that took place, you know,
maybe years ago, it's not even clear you need עדים edim for
the חופה, chupa you know, for formal עדים. edim. If you had,
you had 100 people there of your, of all of your relatives,
got a big family and nobody is a כשר עד, kosher eid,
it's quite possible that, you know, that it's completely okay in terms
of the נישואין nisuin and the חופה. chupa. That might just be
the, you know, like I said, the actualization of the thing that
of the קידושין kiddushin, that took place many years ago might not
need a formal, it's not a formal legal act in the way
that the act of קידושין Kiddushin? was, okay? But it has all
these legal consequences. All right, so בתולה נישאת ליום הרביעי, betulah niset
l'yom harvii, so now we want to know when's the חופה? chupa
So the חופה chupa, is going to be for virgins, the חופה
chupa. was on Wednesday.
ואלמנה, v'almanah, what,
yeah, good question, ואלמנה ליום
החמישי, v'almanah l'yom hachamishi, and a widow or a divorcee on Thursdays.
Why? Now, שפעמיים בשבת בתי דינין יושבין בעיירות, shepaamayim b'shabbat batei dinin
yoshvin baayarot, because two times every week the courts would go to
the, you know, villages and sit in the... and have... and hold
court in the villages, ביום השני וביום החמישי, b'yom hasheni u'v'yom hachamishi,
on Monday and on Thursday, שאם היה לו טענת בתולים היה משכים
לבית דין. she'im haya lo taanat betulim haya mashkim l'veit din.
And so the reason that they would get married on Wednesday is
that if Wednesday night after the wedding, when they first were having
sex and slept together, he realized that she wasn't a virgin because
there was no hymenal bleeding, and therefore he was afraid that she
had, not just that she wasn't a... well, we'll see. What this
טענת בתולים taanat betulim is going to dominate us for the first
פרק. perek. What is טענת בתולים? taanat betulim? It means he's claiming
I slept with her, she wasn't a virgin. Big deal, what does
that mean? So one immediate thing is, well, the amount of the
כתובה is different, 200 זוז zuz, for a virgin, 100 זוז Zuz,
for a non-virgin. I mean, we'll talk about this, obviously, this whole
idea about setting the price on a woman's worth based on whether
they were virgins or not, you know, again, definitely reflects a, you
know, very sort of deeply entrenched societal reality and perspectives, and that
was the reality. We'll talk about that more later. So one issue
is I shouldn't have to pay her the 200 זוז, it's only
100 זוז, she wasn't a virgin. But the more weighty, but the
more weighty reality is that look, we've been married technically speaking, the
קידושין Kiddushin. took place ten years ago, and now she's not a
virgin, right? So I suspect that she actually slept with another man
since the קידושין, kiddushin right, before I've slept with her now the
night of the wedding, and therefore I suspect that she's committed adultery,
okay? And then we have to deal with that claim of adultery,
okay, or possible adultery. So therefore, the wedding would be on Wednesday,
so that if he had this claim, he would show up to
בית דין beit din the next day, Thursday morning, in order to
register this claim. Now, there are a few questions. Number one is
what about having it on Sunday, so you can come on Monday?
The other question is, is this just reflecting a practice that people
did? People, you know, the custom developed to get married on Wednesdays,
so the husbands would be very easy for them to go ahead
and register their complaints, and maybe if they registered, you know, if
they waited too long to register it, maybe people would suspect them
more or something. So, you know, whatever reason it was, this was
a common practice that maybe developed so that they would register it
right away. Or is it, as the גמרא gemara says, and that's
a very reasonable way of reading this whole משנה, mishnah, or the
way the גמרא gemara seems to develop, is not that it was
a practice, but that it was a תקנת חכמים, takanat chachamim, that,
you know, the rabbis said that it has to take place on
Wednesday. We want to make sure that you register your complaint the
next day if you have a complaint. Why would we want to
make sure of that? So basically because if it's possible she did
commit adultery, then it is forbidden for you to continue to be
living with her, and therefore, rather than having you get over it,
and you got so upset, but then you made up the next
morning, and this and that, and you know, if it took a
few days before coming to court, you might decide to let it
go, and we don't make... we don't want to let it go
because we want to make sure that if actually she has committed
adultery, that you are, you know, that you don't continue to live
together, because that would be a violation. So that is sort of
seeing it as a rabbinic institution, which is the way the גמרא
gemara does. That's not clear all from the משנה. mishnah. The משנה
mishnah might have just been that that's why the common practice developed
that way, because men wanted to be
able... Why not Sunday? We'll see about in the גמרא. Gemara.
And also אלמנה Almana why יום חמישי?
Yom Chamishi? Right, what doesn't say why אלמנה Almana is יום חמישי.
Yom Chamishi. The other thing of course to talk about is, you
know, does בתולה Besulah here mean first wedding, first marriage? אלמנה Almana
is clearly, everyone knows what a woman's אלמנה, Almana, everyone knows what
a woman's גרושה. Grusha. So it's on a different day. Let's say
there's a young woman who actually has had sex with a man
before she's married and now she's getting married to this guy and
whatever, this person knows her history, whatever the case is. בעולה, Beulah,
that's a reality, 100 זוז, whatever fine. Okay, what day would she
get married on? It's her first marriage, right? Would she get married
on Wednesday? Would she get married on a different day? Is she
going to announce to the whole world that she's had sex before
her wedding? Right? So presumably, you know, whatever the realities are about
a woman who's already had sex and that the כתובה amount is
different or whatever, I would assume that from a societal perspective any
first marriage is going to be on a Wednesday. You know, if
it's not a first marriage it's on a different day. Okay, but
most of the time we're assuming that the first marriages is going
to be a case of a בתולה. Besulah. גרושה Grusha would be
on יום חמישי. Yom Chamishi. Okay, yes.
What about this idea of making up and deciding that even though
the חתן Chatan finds out that this woman is but they really
care about each other and they're willing to accept it? Is that
imposing our romantic ideas now or do you think those things happen?
No, I mean, the גמרא Gemara no. I mean, that I don't
know, is that romantic? It's like, you know, for whatever reason sometimes
people let things go, you know. I mean, and right? So, I
mean anyway the גמרא Gemara says that, it's not me saying that,
you know. That's like that idea that he might calm down and
be prepared to move on. Yeah, yeah, that's not me making that
up. Now, so I wanted to say one other thing though, it's
a major debate of רש"י ותוספות. Rashi and Tosafot. Let's say he
does come and he says she wasn't a virgin. A, there's the
question like how do you know, what just because there wasn't blood,
how can you actually tell she wasn't a virgin? Fine, whatever. That's
one question. Does he really know enough to say that she wasn't
a virgin based on their first night of sex? But let's say
he does. Okay, we don't know that that meant that she committed
adultery before that she slept with another man.
First of all there's ways you could lose the hymen without having
sex, number one. Number two is doesn't mean that she slept with
a man after קידושין? kiddushin Maybe she slept with a man before
קידושין. kiddushin, How you going to know? And even if it's true,
it's all just his say-so. What are you going to do based
on his say-so? So if you take a look at רש"י, Rashi,
look at the first רש"י Rashi says here, the first narrow line
of רש"י: Rashi: אם היו טענת בתולים ישיב לבית דין בעוד כעסו
עליו im hayu tanat besulim yashiv le-bet din be-od ka-aso alav
while he's still angry, ואם יש
שהיה בינתיים יש לחוש, ve-im yesh shehiyuh bein tayim yesh lachosh, there
you go, here's רש"י Rashi saying it, שמא יתפייס, shemma yitpayes,
maybe he'll be like, you know, consoled or whatever, calmed down, ותתקרר
דעתו ve-titkarer da'ato
and cool off, ויקיימנה ve-yikayemnah and they'll stay married. ושמא זינתה תחתיו
ve-shemma hiznah tachtav and maybe she committed adultery, ונאסרה עליו ve-ne'esra alav
as we learn from כדגמרינן מונסתרה והיא נטמאה, kedi'alfinnan mi-ve-nistra ve-hi nitma'ah,
we learned from סוטה Sotah that a woman is forbidden to her
husband if she commits adultery. ומתוך שיבא לבית דין יתברר הדבר כשיצא
הקול שמא יבאו עדים u-mitoch she-yavo le-bet din yitbarer ha-davar kshe-yaitze ha-kol
shemma yavo'u edim
and if he's going to come to בית דין Beit Din and
make this charge and then everybody starts talking about it, then maybe
witnesses will come and clarify the situation. So for רש"י, Rashi, his
claim isn't really what's going to do it per se. His claim
will raise a ruckus, it'll be registered in court, and then it
will we'll clarify it through witnesses. תוספות Tosafot disagree, and תוספות Tosafot
says from the גמרא Gemara it makes it sounds like there's a
concern even if without witnesses, just his claim alone. Of course his
claim alone can't create, you know, can't prove anything, but there's a
principle called שויה אנפשיה חתיכה דאיסורא. shavyeh anafsheh chaticha de-issura. If you're
claiming she's not a virgin, then you're claiming that she committed adultery
or possibly committed adultery, then as you are bound by your own
claim and therefore you are not allowed to live with her. Not
because we say objectively we know she did it, but because you
have made her forbidden to you by claiming that she has committed
adultery, you are bound by that and that's a principle of שויה.
shavyeh. Now of course it again gets to the point like, I
don't know she did, I just say she's not a virgin, who
knows what that means. Okay, but that's an important debate of רש"י
ותוספות Rashi and Tosafot
whether it is as a result of this witnesses will come or
as a result of this you will sort of be bound by
your own statement. Okay, according to תוספות Tosafot it's harder to understand
why we want to make sure you come to the court. Since
we're not objectively clarifying anything, you're just you're just sort of forcing
this situation on yourself, this status on yourself because of your suspicions
and your claims, not clear why we would want to force it.
Okay, but רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot do agree based on a
גמרא Gemara we're going to see that we try to ensure that
this would come to the court rather than this was just a
practice that grew up.
Just two short things, first of all according to that שיטה shita
of תוספות, Tosafot, why not does not become like a סוטה Sotah
situation?
סוטה Sotah is when you're suspected beforehand and then you warn the
woman and then she whatever, but then there is objective testimony that
she went into private after she was warned. Right, but שויה אנפשיה,
shavyeh
anafsheh, שויה אנפשיה חתיכה דאיסורא. shavyeh anafsheh chaticha de-issura. insulting as a
כשרות kashrus principle being applied to a woman.
Yeah, that's true. חתיכה דאיסורא chaticha d'issura
that's worth pointing out. Right, right, alright, that is true. Okay, but
תוספות Tosafos doesn't explain why we're invested to make sure that you
get the שביה. Shavya. I don't know the answer to that. He
doesn't even raise the question I'm raising. Alright, let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. That was a lot. That was before we
got to the גמרא. Gemara. So, אמר רב יוסף אמר רב יהודה
אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yosef Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel, said רב
יוסף Rav Yosef in the name of רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Rav
Yehuda Amar Shmuel, מפני מה אמרו, Mipnei ma amru, why did they
say בתולה נישאת ליום הרביעי, besulah nisais l'yom harvii, meaning not what
was the purpose for saying it should be Wednesday, but why do
we care that the practice was that they would get married on
Wednesdays? לפי ששנינו, Lefi sheshaninu, because we taught in a later משנה,
Mishna, הגיע זמן ולא נישאו. higia zman v'lo nisu. The time that
they had established for the חופה chupa came and for some reason
they didn't get married. What this means is, and this is where
this idea of a year comes from, it does not mean a
year after קידושין kiddushin they would have חופה. chupa. They might have
had קידושין kiddushin like I said when she was five years old.
Okay, but then when he says, 'Alright honey, you know what, I
think it's time, I think that we have we should actually, you
know, do the חופה chupa and start and start our married life
together.' From that moment on when he says we should actually have
the חופה, chupa. right, then you give her a year to get
ready for the חופה. chupa. So the year is to get ready
for the חופה chupa. from the time that not from the time
of קידושין, kiddushin it might be from the time of the קידושין
kiddushin if they do קידושין kiddushin and say, 'and we're going to
get married as soon as possible,' then that would be a year
from now. Okay, but if you did the קידושין Kiddushin five years
ago, when it says now it's now we should begin having נישואין
nissuin already, from that time, you know, you have a year. And
the reason she has a year is to get ready and to
get her dowry and to get, you know, whatever, get prepared mentally
and financially and in all other ways. So it's a year from
the time that he is תבוע לינשא, tavoa l'innasei, says that it's
time to get married, time to do the נישואין. nissuin. Okay, so
he said that on, you know, on טו בשבט Tu B'shvat in,
you know, 5774. And now it is טו בשבט Tu B'shvat 5775.
Okay, now is the day for the wedding. It just so happens
actually that today is Wednesday. All right, fine. So that's the day
for the wedding. So what happens? It comes along the year later
and for some reason they're not having the חופה. chuppah. He's postponing,
they're having a problem with the caterer, she's postponing, whatever the reason
is, they're not having the חופה chuppah on the day that was
a year after they had said they were going to do it.
הגיע זמן ולא נישאו, higia zman v'lo nisu, the time came and
they're still not married.
אוכלת משלו ואוכלת בתרומה. ocheles mishelo v'ocheles b'terumah.
She eats from his property, meaning he now his marriage obligations kick
in even though they don't have the חופה. chuppah Since they should
be married by this date, the rabbis said he has to start
supporting her as of this date even if they do not yet
have the חופה. chuppah So he she eats from his, you know,
he pays for the food, he, you know, he provides her, you
know, her support starting at this date. And if he is a
כהן, kohen, she can even eat his תרומה, truma, even though normally
you need to have נישואין nissuin to have תרומה, truma, eat תרומה,
truma, you need not just קידושין Kiddushin, but נישואין nissuin to be
נשואה nesua to a כהן. kohen. But nevertheless, since they
should be נשואה nesua by this date, she eats the תרומה. truma.
Now the גמרא's Gemara going to say that therefore really technically speaking
even a woman after קידושין Kiddushin. who's married to a כהן kohen
can eat תרומה. truma. דרבנן D'rabbanan we wait for נישואין. nissuin. We
waived that דרבנן rabbanan requirement because by this date she should have
been נשואה nesua anyway. And by the way, if he has to
pay for her food and he's a כהן, kohen, it's a lot
easier if we allow him to give her תרומה truma than if
we force him to give her non-תרומה. truma. So she can so
he has to give her food starting at this time, but he
can also actually give her but it can be תרומה. truma. And
so that's the הלכה. halacha. So fine. So the obligations kick in
on the wedding day whether you're having the wedding or not.
While she's living with her father still?
While she's still living with her father. So therefore the question is,
יכול הגיע זמן באחד בשבת יהא מעלה לה מזונות? yachol higia zman
b'echad b'shabbas yehei maaleh lah mezonos? Let's say טו בשבט Tu B'shvat
fell out on a Sunday. Right? A year ago טו בשבט Tu
B'shvat he proposed, or not proposed, said we should have the חופה.
chuppah This year it's a Sunday. So from Sunday to Wednesday, does
he have to pay the food bills? You understand the question? Right?
Okay, it's a year later, but it's not yet Wednesday. Okay. So
I might
think so. לכך שנינו בתולה נישאת ליום הרביעי. l'kach shaninu besulah nisais
l'yom harvii.
Therefore it says, no, wedding days are always on Wednesday, so the
wedding date was not exactly a year later. The wedding date was
the first Wednesday a year a year later, right? Like the first
Monday in February is whatever President's Day or second I get confused.
Anyway, so it's the first Wednesday a year after the a year
after they're saying we're getting married, that's the wedding date, not exactly
a year later, and he doesn't have to pay for the food
from from Sunday through Wednesday. That's a very nice application of this
הלכה. halacha.
Is it such a big deal this like layout for the food
like a couple of days?
Who knows?
It's money is money. You don't get rich by giving it away.
Okay, so אמר רב יוסף. Amar Rav Yosef. Okay, so לכך שנינו
בתולה נישאת ליום
הרביעי אמר רב יוסף.
l'kach shaninu
besulah nisais l'yom
harvii Amar Rav Yosef.
So
this was רב יוסף Rav Yosef said this in the name
Why does that answer the question why not on Sunday?
No, so it doesn't. Right? It doesn't answer why and it doesn't
answer why not you're... it's no no no, that's that's not the
question they're asking. The question although it says למפני מה, Lemipnei ma,
which means why did we say it, as תוספות Tosfos points out
it doesn't really mean why, it means like why do I care?
What's the implications of saying it? But still doesn't answer that's the
question you have, that wasn't the question he was answering. We'll get
to your question. All right. So אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef,
so said רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. So רב יוסף Rav Yosef's going
to be bothered by some more questions. רב יוסף Rav Yosef said
this in the name of רב יהודה Rav Yehuda אמר שמואל, Amar
Shmuel, but then he didn't understand this tradition he got from שמואל
Shmuel and he challenged his own teachers. So אמר רב יוסף, Amar
Rav Yosef, מרי דאברהם, Mari d'Avraham, God of Avraham, תלי תניא בדלא
תניא? tali tanya bidla tanya?
You're making something that's in a משנה Mishnah dependent on something that's
not in a משנה? Mishnah? So the גמרא Gemara says what do
you mean? These are both משניות. Mishnayos. So the גמרא Gemara says
האי תניא והאי לא תניא? Hai tanya ve'hai lo tanya? Wait a
minute, which one is in a משנה Mishnah and which one isn't
in a משנה? Mishnah? האי תניא והאי תניא, Hai tanya ve'hai tanya,
they're both משניות. Mishnayos. Our משנה Mishnah about Wednesday and the משנה
Mishnah about having to start paying the food bills. אלא תלי תניא
דמפרש טעמא בתניא דלא מפרש טעמא. Ella tali tanya demefaresh ta'ama bitanya
delo mefaresh ta'ama. Our... you're...
you're making a... a משנה Mishnah that the reason is said explicitly.
It says why it's Wednesday. It's Wednesday so you can come to
בית דין Beis Din the next day. And you're talking about oh
no, so this tells us about what an implication will be in
terms of whether you have to pay the food bills. No, the...
why you... I mean if you want to say that's a הלכה,
Halacha, fine, that's an interesting הלכה, Halacha, but don't tell me this
is the point of teaching this משנה. Mishnah. The point of teaching
this משנה Mishnah is to tell you you do it on Wednesday
so the guy can come to בית דין Beis Din the next
day to tell you for the very reason the משנה Mishnah tells
you, you should know you have to do it... get married on
Wednesday so we want to make sure the guy comes to בית
דין Beis Din the next day. If you want to tell me
another הלכה Halacha that we learned from this about paying food bills,
wonderful, but don't tell me this is the point of teaching this
משנה. Mishnah. So אלא אי איתמר הכי איתמר, Ella ei itmar hachi
itmar, if
it was taught, here's how it was taught. אמר רב... now I
will say by the way that... that it's actually if you think
that the משנה Mishnah is a תקנת בית דין, Takkanas Beis Din,
which is what the גמרא Gemara seems to think, then it's like
so then it's telling
me that... married on Wednesday to tell me we care that he
has an option he's able to come to בית דין Beis Din
the next morning. But if you think that the משנה Mishnah is
just like a common practice that the community sort of has adopted,
then and then you a... then it's a good question. What do
I care what the communal practice is? Why should that matter? Tell
me a... it's very nice that the community decided to get married
on Wednesday so that he would have a court to go to.
What do I care what you know what those מנהגים minhagim are.
So oh, here's a נפקא מינה. nafkamina. The נפקא מינה nafkamina is
whether you have to pay the food bills from Sunday to Wednesday.
So it's very possible that this teaching reflected an understanding that the
משנה Mishnah was not teaching a הלכה. Halacha. The משנה Mishnah was
just telling a practice and then he wanted to tie in this
practice to a practical Halachic implication. But the גמרא Gemara understands that
the משנה Mishnah. is telling a הלכה. Halacha. So what do you
mean, what's the Halachic implication? The Halachic implication is you gotta get
married on Wednesday.
Okay, so quickly... yeah. So we said we have to go to
בית דין, Beis Din, you mean like a בית דין Beis Din
of twenty-three?
No, we'll see that... I understand. We'll see that in the גמרא.
Gemara. אלא אי איתמר הכי איתמר, Ella ei itmar hachi itmar, if
it was said here's how it was said. אמר רב יהודה אמר
שמואל מפני מה אמרו בתולה נישאת ליום הרביעי שאם היה לו טענת
בתולים היה משכים לבית דין. Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel mipnei mah
amru besulah nises leyom harvi'i she'im hayah lo ta'anas besulim hayah mashkim
leveit din. Why... so let's understand the reason in the משנה. Mishnah
The reason in the משנה Mishnah. of Wednesday was so that he
could go to בית דין Beis Din on Thursday morning. Now it
asks the question Jonathan was asking.
ותינשא באחד בשבת שאם היה לו טענת בתולים היה משכים לבית דין.
Vitinasai be'echad beshabas she'im hayah lo ta'anas besulim hayah mashkim leveit din.
So he should also go to the בית דין Beis Din on
Monday. So I don't understand the reason of the משנה. Mishnah Completely
changes the teaching which tied it into this משנה Mishnah about paying
for the food bill. Okay, it's a completely different question and a
completely different answer. And here's the answer. שקדו חכמים על תקנת בנות
ישראל שיהא טורח בסעודה שלושה ימים אחד בשבת ושני בשבת
ושלישי בשבת וברביעי כונסה. Shakdu chachamim al takanas bnos yisrael sheyehe tore'ach
besuda shlosha yamim echad beshabas vesheni beshabas veshlishi beshabas uvervi'i konsah. So
the reason that it was Wednesday and not Sunday was the Rabbis
wanted to ensure that people would spend... the men would spend at
least three days getting the... he had a year... yeah, that was
she had a year to get her trousseau ready.
And so did he.
Yeah, but you know what, guys... you know what... guys wake up
at the last minute. Okay, so... so he is the one that's
making the wedding party and they wanted to make sure that he
invested enough time and effort to make it a nice party. So
therefore if you do it on Sunday, he's gonna wake up מוצאי
שבת. Motzaei Shabbos. So you did it on Wednesday so he would
spend Sunday through Tuesday preparing for the wedding. Okay, שיהא טורח בסעודה
שלושה ימים, sheyehe tore'ach besuda shlosha yamim, Sunday, Monday, and Tuesday and
on Wednesday he would have they would have the חופה.
Okay. In other words the groom's family pays for the wedding.
Exactly. Usually. ואכתי ששנינו, Ve'achti sheshaninu, but now shh, now that we
taught שקדו, shakdu, so now we understand why Wednesday and not Sunday.
And now we're going to in the end we can't forget the
fact that we tried to tie it into this question of who
pays the food bill. So now we're going to do that as
stage two. Now that we understand that the reason of Wednesday was
specifically we said we don't want Monday, we... Sunday, it only has
to be Wednesday, now we can tie it into the question of
who pays the food bill. אותה ששנינו הגיע זמן ולא נישאו אוכלת
משלו ואוכלת בתרומה, Osah sheshaninu higi'a zman velo nisu ocheles mishelo ve'ocheles
bitrumah, that once the date has come she... he pays the food
bill. הגיע זמן באחד בשבת, Higi'a zman be'echad beshabas, if the date
came on a Sunday, he can't say, you know, she can't... So
she can't say, oh, we should have got married on Sunday. Sunday
is just as good as Wednesday, and therefore you have to pay
the food bill. No, Sunday isn't as good as Wednesday, and the
real date is Wednesday. Okay, so even if the year came up
on a Sunday, בתוך שאינו יכול לכנוס, betoch she'eino yachol lichnos, since
he's not able to get married on a Sunday because we insist
that it be no earlier than Wednesday, אינו מעלה לה מזונות, eino
ma'aleh lah mezonot, he does not have to pay for the food
bill. Okay, so therefore what the גמרא Gemara has done is, it
has implicitly said, again, not express but implicit, it has made the
משנה Mishnah not just a question of a common practice, and then
it's a good question, what do I care what the common practice
is? Oh, נפקא מינה nafka mina for the food bill. No, it's
made the משנה Mishna of rabbinic demand that you get married on
a Wednesday so that you'll be able to bring the issues to
the court the next day. And then it actually has made the,
then why Wednesday and not Sunday? And then it's introduced a new
rabbinic point, which is we want to ensure three days to get
ready for the סעודה. seudah. And because of that, therefore there could
be no claim that we should have got married on Sunday. Okay,
because therefore he is being forced like by the rabbis almost to
not have the wedding until Wednesday so the real date becomes Wednesday,
not an earlier date in the week, not on Sunday, and therefore
he doesn't have to pay for the food.
Well obviously that's like a later gloss.
Totally. Of course, totally. לפיכך, Lefikach, therefore, חלה הוא, chala hu, now
that we've introduced the idea that when he is, if you're not
able to do it the day that of, you know, a year
later, here you're not able to do it because the rabbis said
you have to wait till Wednesday, so therefore you don't have to
pay the food bill if it's not out of your
control, therefore says the גמרא, Gemara, other things that are out of
your control, you also wouldn't have to pay the food bill if
the wedding got delayed. לפיכך, Lefikach, חלה הוא, chala hu, if he
got sick, או שחלתה היא, o shechaltah hi, or she got sick,
או שפירסה נדה, o shepirsah niddah, or she became a נדה, niddah,
and you know, there's a whole discussion between the ספרדים Sephardim and
the אשכנזים Ashkenazim whether you can halachically have a חופה when the
woman is a נדה, niddah, since they're not able to have sex
at that time. But even if legally you can, nobody wanted to
have a חופה when the woman was a נדה, niddah. because then
they wouldn't be able to start having sex. So even if it
wouldn't be legally binding, right, if you could also legally have a
חופה when they're sick. But nobody wants to have a חופה when
you're sick either. Okay, so this doesn't mean that legally halachically it
wouldn't work, but these are reasons why.
Pretty much, I mean like legally...
so you'll say she's sick,
okay, או שפירסה נדה, o shepirsah niddah, or she became a נדה,
niddah, אינה מעלה לה מזונות. einah ma'aleh lah mezonot. So in those
cases, since it got delayed and it was nobody's fault, he doesn't
have to pay the food bill. So we're learning from this idea
that when the rabbis say Wednesday, you know, it's not, you know,
then the three-day delay is because of the rabbinic institution, so we're
going to learn from that that any time there's a delay due
to nobody's fault, the husband does not have to start paying the
food bill. Okay, so that's one conclusion. But now the גמרא Gemara
questions that. ואיכא דבעי לה מיבעיא. Ve'ika d'ba'ei lah mibaya.
Some actually raise this as a question. חלה הוא מהו? Chala hu
mahu? What's the story if he got sick? Does he have to
pay the food bills or not? התם טעמא מאי משום דאונס. Hatam
ta'ama mai mishum d'ones. Why does he not pay the food bills
when it's the wedding takes place on a Wednesday, not the Sunday?
Because he's, it's out of his control. הכא נמי אונס. Hacha nami
ones. Here too, it's out of his control, it's not his fault,
so he shouldn't have to pay the food bill. או דילמא, O
dilma, or do we say, התם אונס בתקנתא דתקינו ליה רבנן. Hatam
ones bitkantah d'takinu leh rabanan. There
it was out of his control because of a rabbinic institution. הכא
לא. Hacha lo. Here, not. Now who cares? Either way it wasn't
his fault, but the point is there's an obvious difference. When the
rabbis have been saying, and by the way, notice the phrase תקנתא
דתקינו ליה רבנן. takantah d'takinu leh rabanan. The גמרא Gemara is clearly
making this idea of Wednesday a תקנת רבנן, takant rabanan, a rabbinic
institution. Now there's a big difference between getting sick and knowing that
weddings have to be on Wednesdays. If you know that weddings have
to be on Wednesdays, then from the very outset the wedding date
was not Sunday, Monday, or Tuesday. From the very outset the wedding
date was a year, the first Wednesday starting a year later, right?
A year from now, the first Wednesday at that point. So from
the very beginning, it's not like, oh, it should have been Sunday
but because of some thing out of your control it got postponed.
It didn't get postponed, the date was Wednesday. All right? That's very
different from saying the date was Wednesday and it didn't happen Wednesday
because you got sick. So it might well be, if that's what
happens, the real date came, the Wednesday came, whether it's your fault
or not your fault, you got to start paying the bills starting
on that date. Yes.
This whole discussion is about who's paying the food bill for
those three days? Yeah, yeah. Well, if it's not three days, let's
say he got sick and he's going to be sick for a
year, let's say it's a bad sickness. Who's paying it for the
year? In the discussion of Sunday to Wednesday it was a three-day
question, but for those...
right, that was the question of postponing Sunday to Wednesday. But the
question actually, let's say somebody's having cold feet and they're postponing for
five years, who's paying the food bill at that stage? Right? Okay,
so, so it says look, for the issue of Wednesday, that's not
just that, that's not that it was postponed, that was the automatic
date that was set. But if it actually was postponed, maybe you
start paying starting on the actual wedding date.
When he got cold feet he would have to pay, but she
got cold feet...
Well, that's the question. So right now he's got sick, it's nobody's
fault, okay? If it's somebody's fault, right? Because presumably if it's somebody's
fault, he is... He's the reason, he's willfully delaying it, it would
be obvious you would have to pay. Presumably if she was willfully
delaying it, it would be obvious he wouldn't have to pay. So
that's not a question. If it's somebody's fault, then it follows the
person whose fault it is. The question is it's nobody's fault. But
nevertheless it's postponed. Does he start, does his obligations begin from that
date?
וניתקוף אי שניתקוף אי. v'nitkof ei she-nitkof ei. What?
התם Hasam meaning over there in the case of our mishna, when
the when it got when it took place on a Wednesday and
not a Sunday, okay, that there the Rabbis instituted that. So the
way I'm reading that is there the very wedding date from the
very beginning was a Wednesday. So of course you don't pay before
the Wednesday. But הכא Hacha in this case of getting sick, well,
it's the it actually was postponed from the wedding date. The wedding
date was a Wednesday and he got sick and it didn't happen.
So maybe you start paying starting on the actual wedding date. ואי
תימצי לומר חלה הוא מעלה לה מזונות V'im timtzi lomar chalah hu
ma'aleh lah mezonos if when he gets sick, he does pay, okay,
חלתה היא מה chalsah hi mah what if she gets sick? Right?
So again, if somebody's intentionally postponed at the blame, you follow the
person who's to blame. But here nobody's to blame, but it is
because of somebody, one of them got sick. So does that make
a difference? So if she's the one that got sick, can you
say, I'm not going to pay, it's you're the one that got
sick. I'm not going to start paying you now. Okay, מהו. mahu.
מצי אמר לה אנא קאינא matzi amar lah ana kaina
can he say, look, I'm ready to get married, if you're not
ready to get married because you have 104 fever, I'm not going
to start paying you, you know, for the postponement. It's because of
you we can't start a marriage. או דילמא o dilma or do
we say, מצי אמרה ליה נסתחפה שדהו matzi amrah leh nistachfah sadehu
it's your field that got flooded. In the end, it was your
bad luck. Now, what does it mean it's your bad luck? I
mean, she's the one that got sick. Okay, but certainly if you
look at marriage from the perspective of the man, right, of patriarchal
society, so, you know, you look at it like he's the one
getting married, you know, and he's the one bringing a woman into
his house, and if that got postponed, you sort of see it
as like it was his bad luck, not her bad luck.
That's quite it's definitely it's definitely
how many insulting phrases we have one of them, fine.
Anyway, that is true. If you want to even be more insulting,
turn to תוספות Tosafot on דף ב עמוד ב daf beis amud
beis and it's actually even worse in the תוספות הרא"ש, Tosafot ha-Rosh,
but we'll look at our תוספות Tosafot here on the top of
דף ב עמוד ב. daf beis amud beis. מצי אמרה ליה נסתחפה
שדהו. matzi amrah leh nistachfah sadehu. תוספות Tosafot says ואינו יכול לטעון
דאדרבה מזלא גרים ve-eino yachol liton d'adaraba mazla garem it's her
it's her bad luck. וכיון דלא מיפקדא אפריה ורביה לא מיענשא v'keivan
d'lo mifkda a'pirya v'rivya lo mi'ansha
she wasn't commanded on פריה ורביה, pirya v'rivya, he is, so if
anything bad happens it's seen as a result from, you know, from
his a punishment coming to him from שמים. shamayim. ועוד דאשה היא
שדה של הבעל ואין הבעל שדה שלה. V'od d'ishah hi sadeh shel
ha-ba'al v'ein ha-ba'al sadeh shelah.
Okay, so it's using the phrase of שדהו, sadehu, like his property.
So very much reflecting this whole idea, which we'll have plenty to
talk about when we do קידושין Kiddushin, about the idea of wife
as property. All right, so anyway, the another way to say it
is it's not really a question of whose bad luck it is,
it's just a question of, it doesn't matter. Bottom line is, it's
not like he's willfully postponing it, bottom line is, the obligations begin
starting on the wedding date. It doesn't really matter you know why
it's not happening. As long as nobody is to blame, nobody, you
know, nobody willfully postponed it, then the obligations begin from that date.
Okay, so that's another way of understanding it, much you know, not
exactly נסתחפה שדהו. nistachfah sadehu.
And רש"י Rashi sort of hints to that. If you look at
the last line of רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says here on דף
ב עמוד א, daf beis amud aleph, כלומר מזלך גרם כי מהיום
אני מוטל עליך לזון. klomar mazlacha geram ki mehayom ani mutal alecha
lazon.
So you could sort of say like תוספות Tosafot it's your bad
luck, we view everything through your perspective, but it could just be,
no, the obligations begin today, it doesn't really matter whose fault it
is, as long as it's not willful, as long as it's out
of your control. Okay, so that's that's we don't know whether whether
when she got sick, whether he starts paying. ואי תימצי לומר V'im
timtzi lomar and if you say, אמרה ליה נסתחפה שדהו amrah leh
nistachfah sadehu she can say it's your bad luck and you start
paying even though I'm the one that got sick. פירסה נידה מהו
pirsah niddah mahu let's say she became a נידה, niddah, right? Those
were the three cases we mentioned. He got sick, she got sick,
she became a נידה. niddah. מהו. mahu. בשעת וסתה לא תיבעי לך.
b'sha'as vestah lo tiba'i lach. If it's during her normal cycle, it
could have been expected, this is her period, דלא מצי אמרה ליה
נסתחפה שדהו d'lo matzi amrah leh nistachfah sadehu she can't say it's
your bad luck. This was clearly something that was all about her
and her cycle. So therefore, because of that, it somehow seems like
this is because of her. Not that she again did anything wrong,
she's to blame, but ultimately, you know, it's because of her. Because
of her cycle, therefore, and because it's seen as because of her,
he doesn't have to pay if something that happened, a delay that
happened because of her.
So the wedding really is the first Wednesday after a year when
long she's not a נידה niddah then.
Right. Okay. Now or let's say they decide to get married even
though she is a נידה. niddah. But the presumably what's very clear
here is that in practice, even if הלכתית halachically it would work,
in practice they wouldn't do it. Okay. כי תיבעי לך שלא בשעת
וסתה. ki tiba'i lach shelo b'sha'as vestah. The question is that she
had a, you know, mid-cycle bleeding. Okay, so it's nothing, you know,
that's seen as like coming from שמים. shamayim. That's not coming from
her, right? Her normal cycle, oh that's her. If this is like,
you know, getting sick, you know, it came from outside of her
sort of seen like, you know, it came from שמים shamayim and
therefore it could be all seen as like... bad luck and therefore
he should have to pay. Okay. מאי? Mai? כיון דלא בשעת וסתה
הויה מצי אמרה ליה נסתחפה שדי. Keivan d'lo bish'as vestah havya matzi
amra leh nistachfah sadei.
Since it wasn't during her normal period of the month, she can
say, hey, this was just bad luck and if it's bad luck
it's your bad luck and you got to start paying. או שמא
כיון דאיכא נשי דקמשניא וסתייהו Od shema keivan d'ika nashei d'kamshanya vestayu
or no, sometimes women actually their cycle changes. כשעת וסתה דמי. K'shas
vesta dami. So it's not seen as like getting sick, it's just
seen as a natural thing that happens with women that sometimes their
cycle changes. And since it's seen as coming not מן השמים min
haShamayim but coming from her, although nobody's blaming her, but ultimately she's
the reason why it was delayed, therefore he doesn't have to pay.
So כיון דאיכא נשי דקמשניא וסתייהו כשעת וסתה דמי. Keivan d'ika nashei
d'kamshanya vestayu k'shas vesta dami. So that's the... we don't know the
answer to that. So this assumes that it is not true that
the payments begin... the first approach was that if it's delayed for
any reason you don't pay. This approach takes the opposite assumption, that
fundamentally you start paying on the wedding date, on the Wednesday. Okay,
but is there cases where we could sort of say maybe when
she's seen as the cause of it then you don't pay? Then
the man wouldn't pay. So פשט רב אחאי. pashat Rav Achai. So
רב אחאי Rav Achai sort of wants to conclude this from the
following. הגיע זמן ולא נישאו אוכלת משלו ואוכלת בתרומה. Higia zman v'lo
nisu ochles mishelo v'ochles b'truma.
Okay, it says that when the time came and they didn't get
married, so she... he pays the food bills. לא נשאו לא קתני.
Lo nasu lo katani. It doesn't say in the masculine, the men
didn't marry the women starting on that date. אלא לא ניסתו. Ela
lo nistu. The women, it's like the נפעל. nifal. The women were
not married by the men on that date. Okay, so why is
it framing it in terms of the women? היכי דמי? Heichi dami?
What does that mean? It sounds like somehow the women were the
cause of the delay. אי דקמעכבן אינהו היא I d'kamakvan inu hi
if they are willfully saying I'm not getting married, I'm refusing to
get married today, I'm having cold feet, so then אמאי אוכלת משלו
ואוכלת בתרומה? amai ochles mishelo v'ochles b'truma? Why would he pay the
food bills? It's quite clear that if anybody is making a willful
decision to postpone it then you follow the person who's to blame.
And if she's the one that's making the willful decision then clearly
he would not pay the food bills. So okay, that can't be
the case. So then why does it frame it in terms of
the women? אלא לאו דאיתניס כהאי גוונא. Ela lav d'itnis k'hai gavna.
It must be that it was some type of thing out of
her control but it was nevertheless it was about her. Okay, so
it must be something like she got sick or maybe even something
like she became a נדה. And it's saying that even if she
is the reason why they didn't get married, as long as she's
not willfully postponing it, she still... he still pays the food bills.
אלא לאו דאיתניס כהאי גוונא וקתני אוכלת משלו ואוכלת
בתרומה.
Ela lav d'itnis k'hai gavna v'katani ochles mishelo
v'ochles b'truma. So nice way of reading it. It says if the
women weren't married, suggesting somehow that it might have something to do
with them, and even when it has something to do with them,
he still pays the food bills with the exception of when they
actually very willfully... a woman is very... is willfully postponing it. So
אמר רב אשי. amar Rav Ashi. So רב אשי Rav Ashi rejects
this. לעולם אימא לך כדקתני כל אונסא לא אכלה. L'olam eima lach
k'atanyu kol ones lo achla.
Any type of thing that's out of the control you wouldn't pay.
You never pay if the date is postponed unless the man is
to blame and unless the man is willfully postponing it. Anything that's
out of people's control you would not pay.
So אונס... ones... so חולה, chola, חלצה, chalsah, נדה,
none of those things you pay.
Going back to the first thing we said in the גמרא. Gemara.
Okay, it doesn't matter that nobody was to blame... I mean, if
nobody was to blame then you're not going to pay. Okay, it
does not kick in automatically from that date. If it's an אונס,
ones, nobody pays. לא אכלה. lo achla. ודקמעכבי אינהו. V'd'kamaachvi inhu.
And so when is it that they pay? When the men are
willfully... the groom is willfully postponing. Okay, so that's the only time
they pay. ובדינא הוא דאיבעי ליה למתני לא נשאו. U'vidinah d'iba lei
l'misni lo nasu.
So it should have said the men didn't marry the women. Okay,
because it's only would be when the men are willfully postponing. ואיידי
דתנא רישא בדידי V'aydi d'tana reisha bididi but since the beginning of
that משנה Mishna, talks about the women, we'll see it when we
get to that משנה, Mishnah תנא נמי סיפא בדידי, tana nami seifa
bididi, the end of it also focuses on the women but it
doesn't really mean that the women are choosing not to marry, it
means the men are choosing... are the ones... are the men are
the ones that are choosing not to marry the women. So we
basically have: when do these obligations kick in? Does it kick in
automatically from the date, not from the first day a year later
but from the first Wednesday a year later? And it really doesn't
matter who's to blame, I mean it doesn't really matter why it
was postponed. The only exception would be that if the woman was
willfully postponing it then obviously there would be no obligations on the
man. But with the one exception with the woman obviously postponing, when
that date comes the man has to pay regardless, it doesn't matter
why it was postponed. Or is it the opposite? That there's no
payments just because it's postponed, that doesn't mean that the guy has
to pay. The only time the guy pays is if he's to
blame, if he's the one willfully pushing off the date. But if
it's not him willfully postponing it, if it's something out of people's
control, then obviously you're not. two very different approaches, whether it starts
with a question of blame, is it only when there's blame to
be assigned does he start paying, or does it start with a
question, no, when the date comes, that's when you start paying, right,
again, unless the woman actually it's her fault, but other than that
the fundamental principle is when the date comes you start paying. Okay,
and then interesting questions about like, you know, this interesting middle case
of חולה ונידה cholah venidah etc. But those are the two basic
approaches, yes.
It's interesting, it's the exact same argument in the first סוגיא sugya
of קידושין, kiddushin a related topic in terms of why the language
is...
oh, the masculine and the feminine, yes, it's an
interesting point, I didn't realize.
Okay, so before we now turn to the next point, because that
was a whole little interesting digression about something that's going to be
later on, I will say, you know, Rabbi Dov mentions like the
opening of קידושין. Often opening of מסכתות are, first of all, this
is, this is not a classic opening or whatever, a distinctive opening
of a מסכתא. masechta Often an opening of a מסכתא masechta doesn't
have any אמוראים Amoraim listed. It's a big section of סתם. stam.
And one of the goals of an opening of a מסכתא often
will be, will be to introduce you to themes that are going
to come up. So it is interesting here
that
it's introduced us to a major theme of כתובות like in my
introductory discussion. A major theme is not to hyper, not don't hyperfocus
on this question about טענת בתולים, ta'anat betulim, which is going to
all be our focus for the first פרק. perek. Was she a
בתולה betulah that wedding night, you know, or two hundred or a
hundred, but to make us think about the broader aspect, the broader
themes here are about the ongoing, right, reciprocal obligations when they're actually
married. So we've already now just as a result of talking about
if it's postponed, when do those obligations kick in, we've introduced us
to that reality, that when the marriage begins, you start having these
types of obligations. So it has done that nice job of introducing
us to that. Okay, and along the way, we've, we've understood that
the גמרא Gemara besides the fact that the גמרא Gemara wants to
ensure that it says it wants to ensure that the groom spends
three days preparing for the wedding,
we also introduced the idea that it's taking this משנה Mishna, of
when to say and reading it as a rabbinic תקנה. takanah. By
the way, before we get to the next point, I should say,
תוספות Tosafot says, I don't understand, if you just want him to
be able to go to the בית דין Beit Din Thursday morning,
why don't they get married Wednesday night, right, which is halachically Thursday?
Why are they getting married Wednesday day, why not Wednesday night?
And תוספות Tosafot says,
because there often will be a lot of fights about the כתובה,
and if you waited till Wednesday night, then it might get delayed
and not take place. So you start early Wednesday morning and then
even if you have all these fights or whatever, they'll get hopefully
resolved so you'll be able to get married in time. Which is
I just thought quite fascinating about that reality when the כתובה was
a real financial document, there could have been a lot of fights
and arguments around whether you're, around,
not necessarily, but anyway, about about some of those specifics, you know.
And I do want to tie that in by the way, I
mean now it's just a pro forma document, so you know you
never hear about fights about the כתובה, but I do want to
actually tie it in to something that's happened to me once, which
is, you know, we have a requirement here at אוהבי תורה Ohavay
Torah and also like the international rabbinic fellowship that no rabbis can
do weddings without doing a prenuptial agreement.
And the first time that I actually was מסדר קידושין, mesader Kiddushin,
you know, I was obviously insistent on a prenuptial agreement and I
should have seen warning signs because in preparing the bride and groom
for the wedding, the groom came from a, his parents had a
very nasty divorce and he was raising all of these issues and
questions about the prenuptial agreement. Long story short, you know, we were
going to do it at the wedding in order to make like
a nice thing about it, but do like at this טיש tish
sometimes they sign the prenup. Anyway, comes the wedding and he and
he's refusing to sign the prenuptial agreement. So, I don't want to
go into the details of how I handled that, probably not so
well, but anyways, it was my first קידושין, so that was wonderful.
But certainly, but from there I learned a lesson, which is I
now insist that the prenup be signed and notarized like two weeks
before the wedding, you know, and if, and without that, I'm not
going to do the wedding. So, and then you want to make
a little say at the טיש, tish, hey we signed this prenup,
good, you could say it, but I'm not waiting to sign it
at the actual wedding itself. Okay, so it's just I think it's
an interesting contemporary application of this idea, if you've got a real
document to sign, you don't want to wait till the last minute
because then then people are going to, then who knows what types
of issues people are going to come up with. All right, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this, אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
middle here by the two dots, אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so you
see that it's only the first day and we're already behind. ולענין
גיטין אינו כן. Ul'inyan gittin eino kein. This issue that we've been
raising that if it's an אונס, ones, if it's out of somebody's
control, then they don't have to basically like, you know, bear the
consequences as it were, he doesn't, well, that's not the same by
a גט. get. What does
that
mean by a
גט? get? Let's, well, let's take a look. Okay, I'm going to
wait for the גמרא Gemara to spell it out. אלמא קסבר רבא,
Alma kasvar Rava, so you see רבא Rava is of the position
אין אונס בגיטין, Ein ones b'gittin, because what we're trying to... we
concluded just at the end of the discussion was that there was
a טענת אונס, taynas onus, that if something happened out of your
control you don't have to pay for the מזונות, mezonot, you, the
man, would not have to pay for the מזונות. mezonot. Okay, but
you have to
get her for the...
Michael, let me just let me talk. Okay, so if if there's
an אונס onus the man does not have to pay. Okay, if
רבא's Rava saying it's not true by a גט, get, that means
by a גט get the fact that there was an אונס onus
does not is not a factor. Meaning by the payment for the
מזונות, mezonot, the food bills, the fact that it's an אונס onus
is a factor. You should have been paying starting Wednesday ט״ו בשבט,
Tu B'shvat, okay, the wedding didn't take place, okay, אונס onus is
a factor. We will factor in the fact that it's an אונס
onus and we will consider that so you don't have to pay
your bill. So אונס onus is a factor when it comes to
paying the food bills, you know, in what we've been discussing. But
אונס onus is not a factor. That is a way of thinking
about translating this phrase because it'll get a little confused. אין אונס
בגיטין ein onus begittin means the fact that there was some אונס
onus is irrelevant. It's not a factor to be considered. By paying
the food bills it's a factor to be considered, not by the
issue of גט. get. אלמא קסבר רבא אין אונס בגיטין. Alma kasavar
Rava ein onus begittin. Being- having some אונס onus is not a
factor by גט. get. What does this mean? מנא ליה לרבא הא?
Mina lay lei Rava ha? Where does he get this? So by
talking about where he gets this from we'll see what what this
means. Okay, אילימא מהא דתנן Ileyma me'ha de'tnan from what we learned
in the משנה, Mishna הרי זה גיטך אם לא באתי מכאן עד
שנים עשר חודש. Harei zeh gittech im lo basi mikan ad shneim
asar chodesh. This is your גט get if I don't return within
12 months. Now the reason a man might be saying this is
because he's going off to war or business or whatever overseas and
she'll be left as an עגונה. agunah. So he won't know if
he's alive or dead. So he says if I don't return within
12 months, this גט get you're divorced, this גט get will be
binding. ומת בתוך שנים עשר חודש U'meis betoch shneim asar chodesh and
he died within the 12 months. So at the end of the
12 months, right, he didn't return. So is it a גט? get?
Now why do I care? She's a widow. I care because so
she won't have to do יבום, yibbum, right? That's why you also
want to give a גט get so that your- that the woman
doesn't have to- it's better to be a divorcee than a widow
from that perspective. So what's the הלכה? halacha? He died within 12
months,
אינו גט. eino get.
Now why is it not a גט? get? He didn't return. The
reason it's not a גט get is because he's dead because a
גט get takes effect at the end of the 12 months and
at the end of the 12 months, as רש״י Rashi says,
אין המתים מגרשין, ein hameisim megarshin, it's like לא המתים יהללו יה,
lo hameisim yehallelu yah, so okay, אין המתים מגרשין. ein hameisim megarshin.
If he's dead he can't give the גט. get. Of course, you
know, in ישיבה they love asking this question: Why did רש״י Rashi
have to say that when you're dead you can't divorce your wife?
Why didn't he say she's already a widow so there's no קידושין
to be severing at that moment? Like okay, I'm not sure רש״י
Rashi would have made a difference between those two. The point is
אין גט לאחר מיתה, ein get achar misah, that's what it says.
Okay, yes, the condition was met but nevertheless it doesn't work. Okay,
anyway that's the principle. Okay, that it doesn't take effect. But let's
see how the גמרא Gemara reads it. So מתו דאינו גט meiso
de'eino get because he died. The גמרא Gemara is- that's why it
doesn't take effect because you know a גט get can't take effect
after a guy's dead. חלה הרי זה גט, Chala harei zeh get,
if he got sick, then let's say the reason he didn't return
in the 12 months he was trying to return but the reason
he didn't return was because he got sick. The implication of this
would be that it would be considered like the condition had been
met, right, like he didn't return and the גט get would be
effective. The אונס onus would not be a factor. Right? Is that
clear? Meaning here's the scenario. Why did he not return when he
died? It was out of his control. He was an אונס. onus.
Nevertheless we say that the condition was met. The only reason the
גט get isn't good is because אין גט לאחר מיתה. ein get
achar misah. So if it were a parallel case where he got
sick and he didn't return, we would say the condition was met,
the גט get is binding, and we wouldn't factor in the fact
that the reason he didn't return was that he got an אונס.
onus. Okay? So it's a pretty good deal, right? The fact that
it was out of his control is not relevant. It is not
a factor in determining whether the גט get should take effect. Okay,
so that's what the גמרא Gemara says, מתו דאינו גט חלה הרי
זה גט. Meiso de'eino get chala harei zeh get. So that's why
רבא Rava gets the understanding that being out of somebody's control is
not a factor in הלכות גיטין. hilchos gittin. So the גמרא Gemara
says one minute ודילמא לא אימא לך v'dilma lo eima lach maybe
I could tell you חלה נמי אינו גט chala nami eino get
that even when he gets sick it's not a גט. get. Okay?
Maybe if it was out of his control it's not like the
condition was met
and therefore it is not a גט. get. Now it gets a
lot confusing, a lot of double negatives. He said, if I don't
return, it'll be a גט. get. So actually, he didn't return, the
condition was met. We don't factor in the fact that he was
an אונס onus to make it like even though the condition was
met, it's like it's not met because it was out- because it
was out of his control.
I mean he'd die in war.
Right, that's- I understand. Well, no, the point was that we wouldn't.
No. But okay, but-
so the fact that anyway that was out of his control wasn't
the factor. So the גמרא Gemara says maybe it is a factor.
Maybe if somebody wants to return and can't return because they're sick
then maybe it's like they did return. Okay? And therefore it's like
the condition of the גט get wasn't met and therefore the גט
get is not valid. But it's a lot- funny. If it's because
it's an אונס onus it's like he did return and because it's
like he did return, therefore it's not a גט. get. Okay, you
gotta sort
of... But anyway, maybe the fact that it was out of his
control would be a factor and therefore it actually normally would be
a גט. get. Okay,
so, I'm sorry, actually would not be a גט. get.
Like a disaster.
Right, well that's what the גמרא's Gemara going to get to at
the end of the דף or we'll get to it tomorrow, which
is then you never know if conditions were met and that's why
just from a social policy reason, exactly, and that's what the גמרא's
Gemara going to say later, just from a simple policy position, you
have to say we can't factor in the question of maybe an
אונס oness occurred, because then you'll never know, right? Okay, that's going
to be true and we'll get to that tomorrow. But let's just
read right now: ודלמא לעולם כדאמרי לך חלה נמי אינו גט, vedilma
le’olam k’omlach chala nami eino get, that even if you got sick,
it would be like that would be factored in and it would
be like you returned and therefore it would not be a גט,
get, so being sick would be a factor. והיא גופא קמשמע לן
דאין גט לאחר מיתה, vehi gufa k’mashma lan d’ein get l’achar mita,
and the reason it's talking about dying is not to tell you
what would be the הלכה halacha if he got sick, it's just
to tell you that in the case of dying, there's no, you
know, it doesn't work because of אין גט לאחר מיתה, ein get
l’achar mita, because the guy is dead. Now again, this is a
little funny because before you get to, right, the first position of
the גמרא Gemara was a reasonable one. Before you get to the
idea of אין גט לאחר מיתה, ein get l’achar mita, if אונס
oness counts, then the reason the גט get didn't take effect was
because it was out of the guy's control and it's like he
returned and therefore it's like there's no גט. get. Is that clear,
or everybody's thoroughly confused at this stage? I think everybody's thoroughly confused.
Anyway, the גמרא's Gemara point is that the משנה is trying to
tell you the הלכה halacha that the גט get doesn't take effect
because he's already dead. You're not, it's not trying to infer from
it what would be a parallel case if he got sick. Could
very well be that if he got sick and he was trying
to return, we would factor in the issue of אונס. oness. It
is, but who knows, we don't know what the הלכה halacha is
about getting sick. All it's focusing on is that it doesn't work
if he's dead because a גט get doesn't take effect after a
guy's dead. That's the point. We're not getting into the questions of
when a condition is or is not met out of somebody's control,
that's a different conversation. Okay, so we will pick up with this
tomorrow. I hope, I think that by now people are completely confused.
It's so confused because it's, you know, double negatives start kicking in
here. But the basic idea is clear, is an obvious question, which
is: does it matter if it was out of somebody's control? And
as Jonathan pointed out, it would be impossible to run any society
and any הלכה halacha if we never knew what happened and we
would never know when conditions were met, but we have to explain,
you know, we have to demonstrate that. Okay.